Finding Aid for the The Alma Elizabeth Gault Papers
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
The Alma Elizabeth Gault Papers
Undated
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0167
.84 linear feet
CHRONOLOGY
Sept. 28, 1891 Born in Farnwood, OH; daughter of Dorison Stewart and Nancy Emma Stark Gault
1906-1910 Attended Wells High School, Steubenville, OH
1916 Ph.B., College of Wooster, Wooster, OH
1918 Attended Vassar Training Camp
1918-1920 Attended Philadelphia General Hospital School of Nursing
1922-1925 Clinic Nurse in Tuberculosis, Ohio State Department of Health
1926-1927 Clinic Nurse in Pediatrics, Johns Hopkins Hospital
1927-1937 Associate Director and Instructor in Public Health Nursing, Cooke County School of Nursing (Chicago)
1936-1937 Attended course at Philadelphia School of Health and Social Work; University of Chicago
Summers, 1927-1930 Instructor in Nursing, University of Florida
1938-1943 Director, Union Memorial Hospital School of Nursing
1943-1944 Director of Nursing Service, Memorial Hospital, Springfield, Illinois
1944-1953 Director, Meharry Medical College School of Nursing
1953-1967 School of Nursing, Vanderbilt University
1953-1959, Associate Professor
1958-1959, Acting Dean
1965-1967, Dean
1968 Consultant, Tennessee Mid-South Regional Medical Program
July 12, 1981 Died in Ohio
Scope and Content Note
The Alma Elizabeth Gault Papers consist of two Hollinger boxes (0.834 linear feet).
The collection contains writings by Alma Gault including correspondence, speeches and addresses, journal articles, and class notes and papers from her days as a student at the University of Chicago. Additionally, the collection includes meeting minutes and reports, awards, clippings, photographs and a tape recording of Alma Gault Day.
- Outgoing Correspondence, 1937-1934 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Incoming Correspondence, 1925-1974 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence re: S. Lillian Clayton (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Vassar Training Camp (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Personal data and professional certificates (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Advisory Committee, Southern Missionary College (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Council on Nursing, Tennessee League for Nursing (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Clippings and photographs (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Professional awards (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Community Service Awards (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Alma Gault Day: Original source materials and memorabilia (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Alma Gault Day: Tape recordings of proceedings (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Papers for University of Chicago courses, 1937 (see also Box 2, Folders 5 & 6) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Addresses, 1932-1968: Present Day Needs in Nursing Education, 1932; Nursing in Hospitals and Institutions, 1940; Christmas message from the Union Memorial Hospital School of Nursing, 1941; Problems Facing the Director of the Affiliating School, 1943; The value of Inservice Program of Education, 1948; Nursing’s Professional Reach – Twenty Years of Growth and Development, 1953; Untitled, 1965; The Past Is Prologue, 1965; Well, What Do You Know, 1966; All School Dinner Speech, 1968; Tennessee A & I student nurses night, 1968; LPN Graduation Address, Metro schools, 1968; LPN graduation address, Metro schools. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Addresses, undated: Social Service in Hospitals, The Place of the Nurse in the Public Health Field, Harriet Fulmer, Scenes from a Freshman Week in a School of Nursing, Federal Legislation Relating to Nursing, untitled speech on public health. (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Articles, 1932-1962: Social Service in Hospital, 1937; Nursing in Hospitals and Institutions, 1939; Before the Term Begins in the School of Nursing, 1941; Behaviors of Students in Relation to Fundamental Needs of Patients, 1953; Book review, American Nursing – History and Interpretation, 1954; Follow Up Study of Cancer Patients, 1954; Review of A Bio- Bibliography of Florence Nightingale, 1962; “Ella Phillips Crandall” for Notable American Women (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Articles, undated: The Special Nurse, An Educational Program for the Southern Region, What Recent Trend in Social and Economic Conditions in the Health Field Need to be Considered in Planning Educational Programs for Nurses; Nursing Education Today and Tomorrow; Next Steps for Integration of Negro Nurses as Participants in Nursing Organizations; The Student Health Services in Relation to Nursing Education in Tuberculosis; Nursing Standards as Exemplified in the Public Health Nursing Act; The Library in the School of Nursing; The Adjustment of the Affiliating Student in the Teaching Program; Functions of Alumnae Associations and Their Relations to State and National Associations; The Nursing Supply and Demand As It Affects Institutions; What the Out Patient Department Has to Offer the Student Nurse; The Departmental Budget; Some Observations of a Health Film Showing (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Complete journals containing Miss Gault’s articles: Nursing Care of Erysipelas, 1926; Pioneer Hospital and Nursing Service in Illinois, 1932; Basic Requirements for Intelligent Nursing, 1933; Nurses and Budget Making, 1934; Harriet Fulmer, 1935; Social Service in Hospital, The Library in the School of Nursing, 1937; Before the Term Begins in the School of Nursing, 1941; Nursing’s Professional Reach, 1954; Miss Gault’s Response to the service award of the NLN, 1969. (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Bibliographies on Florence Nightingale; From the collections at the Duke University Medical School and Wayne State University. (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Class notes from University of Chicago courses. (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Class notes from University of Chicago courses. (Box 2, Folder 6)
- MOVED TO MAP CASE:
  - Drawer 1:
    - Early photograph of group of nurses (undated)
    - Diploma – Public Schools of Jefferson County (Ohio), June,1906
    - Diploma – College of Wooster, July, 1916
    - Diploma – Philadelphia General Hospital School of Nursing, 1920
    - Certificate, Registered Nurse – Commonwealth of Pennsylvania, October, 1920
    - Certificate, Registered Nurse – State of Ohio, March, 1923
    - Certificate, Registered Nurse – State of Illinois, July, 1929
    - Certificate, Public Health Nurse – State of Illinois, October, 1931